On the Order of Created Things
by Isidore of Seville
Chapter One Concerning the Faith of the Trinity.
The structure of the universe can be understood in two ways: in God, and in things, meaning the Creator and creatures.
This doesn't mean we consider God a part of creation or that the Creator can be equated with the creature, but because everything that exists is understood as either made or unmade, either powerful or subject, either eternal or temporary.
So, what is made, subject, and temporary is the creature.
But what is unmade, powerful, and eternal is God.
The Holy Trinity—Father, Son, and Holy Spirit—is inseparable in substance, meaning one divinity.
And in the subsistence of persons, an undivided Trinity, where nothing is inferior, nothing superior, nothing before, and nothing after, in the nature of divinity.
Nothing is servile, nothing subject, nothing confined to a place, nothing temporary, nothing weak, nothing growing, nothing related to sex or appearance, and nothing corporeal can be sensed.
But there is one God without beginning, eternal without place, wholly everywhere, arranging all changeable things of creatures without changing Himself.
He sees past, present, and future times equally; for Him, nothing is past, nothing remains, but all is present.
Nothing good displeases Him, nothing evil pleases Him; nothing naturally evil is created by Him, which by itself is nothing but the fault of created good.
Therefore, He is good without quality, great without quantity, eternal without time, principal without position, infused into all creatures, though He has no place; no creature can contain Him, no intelligence can comprehend Him.
One Almighty God, the Holy Trinity—Father, Son, and Holy Spirit.
Therefore, God the Father Almighty has no origin from anything.
He is the source of divinity, from whom the Son, God Almighty, is begotten without time.
The Son is not created because He is God.
Aside from being the Son, He shares everything with the Father in divinity: in eternity, in will, in power, and in wisdom.
Likewise, the Father, aside from being the Father, shares everything with the Son.
The Holy Spirit is God Almighty, not begotten because He is not the Son, not created because He is not a creature, but proceeding from the Father and the Son.
Aside from being the Holy Spirit, He shares everything with the Father and the Son.
He who is the Father is not the Son or the Holy Spirit in person; nor is He who is the Son the Father or the Holy Spirit; nor is He who is the Holy Spirit the Father or the Son.
But in essence, what the Father is, the Son and the Holy Spirit are; and what the Son is, the Father and the Holy Spirit are; and what the Holy Spirit is, the Father and the Son are.
There is not a triple number of gods in that Trinity; for while the persons are distinct, everything of divinity is shared.
The Son, in time, took on human flesh, which is without fault.
He had the nature of humanity, a prudent, intellectual, and wise soul, except for the divine nature, having it so that humanity might become whole.
This is why the Son, who is eternal with God the Father, assumed it, so that He who was the Son of God in divinity would be the Son of Man in humanity.
In this humanity, He was born of the Holy Spirit and Mary, ever Virgin; not because He is to be believed to be the Son of both the Holy Spirit and Mary, but because He was conceived by the power and work of the Holy Spirit, and born of the Virgin.
The suffering of the cross was endured in the flesh, not in divinity.
He suffered death for our redemption and salvation.
After being buried for three days, by divine power, He rose again in the same flesh.
After instructing the one, holy, catholic Church with His word, strengthening it by example, firming it with grace, and securing it with peace, He ascended with all human nature, except for that which is subject to corruption, returning to the Father, from whom He never departed.
He sits at the right hand of the Father, from where He will come again to judge the living and the dead, to reward the just with eternal rewards and the wicked with eternal punishments, in the glory of the Father.
This is the catholic faith.
Believing and confessing this is more beneficial than discussing it.
Neither secular wisdom nor worldly philosophy, which follow the images of things rather than the understanding of truth, could recognize this.
But apostolic faith has handed it down, and the vigilance of the Church protects it.
Chapter Two On Spiritual Creatures
After briefly discussing the vastness of the Creator, let's now consider the order of creatures.
Our aim is not to create new interpretations, but to follow the guidance of Holy Scripture and the explanations of our predecessors, even if only in a small way.
Every creature is either spiritual or physical.
Since creatures consist of intellectual spirits, which are not bound by flesh, and human souls, which are enclosed in flesh, we must first discuss the different ranks of heavenly spirits.
According to Holy Scriptures, there are nine ranks of these spirits: seraphim, cherubim, thrones, dominions, principalities, powers, virtues, archangels, and angels.
Isaiah saw the seraphim standing above the exalted throne of the Lord and heard them singing.
One of them was sent to him, and he was cleansed of the pollution of his mouth.
The cherubim, depicted in the oracle of testimony, covered the mercy seat and the ark, and in the temple of the Lord, they were painted with oxen and lions by Solomon.
Ezekiel also describes seeing a chariot in the visions of God, which he mystically connects with the four Scriptures of both Testaments.
The Apostle Paul, writing to the Colossians, mentions thrones, dominions, principalities, and powers:
Colossians 1:16, "Whether thrones, or dominions, or principalities, or powers."
He also speaks about virtues to the Ephesians, saying:
Ephesians 1:21, "Above all principality, and power, and virtue, and dominion."
The divine volumes are filled with references and mentions of archangels and angels.
The nine precious stones Ezekiel speaks of symbolize the nine orders of these heavenly beings.
Under the guise of the prince of Tyre, the prophet's words lament the highest angel who fell.
It says:
Every precious stone was your covering: carnelian, topaz, and jasper, chrysolite, onyx, and beryl, sapphire, carbuncle, and emerald
(Ezekiel 28:13).
He is described as being covered with these nine stones, representing the nine orders of spiritual duties he once led.
Since we've discussed the number, let's also delve into the different levels of these duties.
Seraphim, meaning burning or igniting, are named so because they burn with God's love more than any other rational creature, thanks to a special gift of divine grace.
Excelling all creatures, they approach the Creator with a unique privilege of divine love and stand in such an exalted honor that no other spirits come between them and the Lord.
The second order includes cherubim, who are counted among the heavenly citizens.
Their name means the multitude of knowledge.
Their intellect is refreshed by closely adhering to the contemplation of God, expanding with a greater multitude of knowledge than all other intellectual creatures.
For those who gaze sharply into the mirror of divine clarity, the hidden secrets of creatures cannot remain concealed.
The third order of intellectual spirits comprises the hosts of thrones, interpreted as seats.
On these, the Lord sits by special grace, exercising His judgments upon all creatures in a terrifying and wondrous manner.
Hence, the Psalmist says:
You have sat on the throne, judging righteousness
(Psalm 9:5).
And in the Revelation of John, the angel speaks: "And the one who sits on the throne will protect them."
At the fourth level of the heavenly offices are the dominions, which surpass in greatness the ministries of the five levels below them. They are placed above others in magnitude of power, and the subordination of the others is shown through obedience.
Next, at the fifth level, are the principalities of the heavenly citizens. They are entrusted with the leadership of the good spirits to carry out the ministries of God.
At the sixth level are the powers. These good spirits have received the authority from the Lord to govern various powers and restrain the wickedness of evil spirits, ensuring they do not exercise cruelty or cling to human senses beyond what is permitted.
The seventh level of spiritual ministries are called virtues, through whom the spirits often perform powers, signs, and miracles among humans.
The eighth order is the archangels, the chief messengers. They announce the greater messages to humans, bringing higher things to human knowledge by the command of the Lord.
The ninth order of the heavenly ministers are called angels. They announce and advise humans on the lesser and common things according to the will of God.
Furthermore, it should be known that whenever angels are named, they take their names from their duties when they come to humans. The highest society of heavenly citizens does not need proper names. For example, Michael means "Who is like God?" because he is destined to be sent against the one who will rise against God in the end. Gabriel, meaning the strength of God, is sent to Zechariah and the Virgin Mary to foretell what nature denied would happen.
To Tobias, Raphael, meaning the Medicine of God, is sent. He who brought health by divine power is rightly called the medicine of God.
And what can happen individually can also occur in ranks, so when one person performs another's duty, they are also called by that person's name.
As it is said: "He makes his angels spirits" (Psalm 104:4).
That is, when He wills, He makes all these angels spirits, meaning messengers.
Sometimes, due to the closeness of other ranks, some take on the duties of other ranks.
Just as from the proximity of thrones, Scriptures say that the Lord also sits above the cherubim.
As it is written in the psalm: "You who sit above the cherubim, shine forth" (Psalm 80:1).
In that heavenly society, what one holds in particular is shared by all in common, because each one is as refreshed by what they see in another as by what they possess themselves.
When they are sent, God, from whom they are refreshed, is never absent from their contemplation.
Not that those spirits who are sent can be everywhere at once, but the Lord, who is everywhere, is always seen by those who move about, in every place without changing Himself.
Hence it is written: "Thousands upon thousands served him, and ten thousand times ten thousand stood before him" (Daniel 7:10).
Both tasks are performed equally by the heavenly powers; they minister when they are sent, and they stand by when they contemplate.
Sometimes, however, the angels who are sent announce directly to the people they come to, and sometimes they send others, as if subordinate to them, for the task of announcing.
As it is read in Daniel, "Gabriel, make this man understand the vision" (Daniel 8:16), which is undoubtedly said by someone superior.
Chapter Three Of the waters which are above the firmament.
Since we've started discussing the order of creation, which your proposition has included, after briefly touching upon the spiritual creation, let's try to explain what the authors have thought about the waters above the firmament.
When light was created on the first day, which is understood to be the spiritual creation, the firmament was made on the second day.
This firmament divided the waters above from the waters below, as Scripture states in Genesis 1:6-7.
From this, we understand that the waters above the firmament are positioned higher than all physical creation.
Although in Psalm 148, after mentioning the firmament, the sun, the moon, and the stars, it refers to the waters above the heavens to show they are higher than all physical creations, the Psalmist places the heavens first when summarizing the dwellings of the highest powers, saying:
"Praise Him, heavens of heavens; and waters that are above the heavens, praise the name of the Lord" (Psalm 148:4).
This shows that after those spiritual spaces, whatever they may be, where the spiritual orders reside, which the prophet calls the heavens of heavens, the waters were established before this visible heaven as the beginning of physical things.
However, to prevent anyone from associating them with the spiritual creation, he placed them after the heavens of heavens, and before mentioning the earth, he added shortly after:
"Praise the Lord from the earth, dragons, and all abysses" (Psalm 148:7).
See, the Psalmist says that these waters are placed above the heavens, yet he places the heavens of heavens before them.
This demonstrates that there are realms positioned between the two heavens; they are lower than the spiritual heavens but higher than the physical heavens.
However, they are still considered part of the physical creations, as they were made on the second day of creation and exist above the physical firmament.
The usefulness of these realms in relation to physical things is explored by teachers in two ways.
Some say they were reserved by God's foresight for the destruction of the world during the flood under Noah, as narrated in Genesis.
Scripture says:
"And the windows of heaven were opened, and it rained for forty days and forty nights"
(Genesis 7:11).
Since clouds, which irrigate the earth with their rains, and even the air, which contains all hemispheres and breezes, are often referred to as heavens in the divine Scriptures, it is said:
"And He rained manna upon them to eat, and gave them bread from heaven"
(Psalm 78:24);
And in another place:
"The heavens shall give rain, and the earth shall yield its fruit"
(Psalm 67:7).
Some teachers believe that an abundance of water was spread from this lower heaven of the clouds, so that, according to the usual custom, the clouds poured out a great amount of rain, with Scripture mentioning the windows being opened because more water than usual was sent down.
Others, however, assert that these waters placed above the firmament were meant to temper the heat of the fire that burns in the luminaries and stars, so that the lower regions would not be scorched by excessive heat.
Chapter FourAbout the Firmament of the Sky.
After discussing the waters of bodily creatures, the firmament appears to be second in order, created on the second day, as previously mentioned, and it separates the waters above from those below.
As for its nature, some believe it covers the earth like a disc, while others think it encircles all creation like an eggshell.
Both views have their supporters.
The Psalmist's words, "You stretch out the heavens like a tent" (Psalm 104:2), do not contradict either viewpoint.
Just as an animal's skin covers its flesh evenly from all sides, forming either a flat or curved surface when stretched out, the firmament can be understood in either way.
Therefore, whether it covers the earth like a stretched-out tent or encircles the world like an animal's hide, both assertions are plausible.
As for whether the firmament is empty and penetrable or solid and firm, various authors have different views.
I'll focus on their opinions rather than their names.
Those who believe the firmament is empty and penetrable compare it to the nature of all elements.
They argue that the earth is the heaviest of all bodily creatures and occupies the lowest place because it can only support itself.
Water is much lighter than the earth but still heavier than air.
Air, unable to sustain itself under water, will escape to its own space if forced beneath it.
The nature of fire is understood to be above the air.
This is easily proven by the fact that when a fire ignites on earthly materials, it immediately directs its flame upwards, towards the regions above the air, where there is an abundance and place for it.
But, extinguished by the surrounding denser air, it quickly vanishes into the soft air, unable to reach its natural place.
This demonstrates that the nature of fire, which ascends, is lighter than air, just as the nature of water, which descends, is shown to be heavier.
Therefore, by this reasoning, the space of the firmament, which is above the fire, is thought to be lighter and thinner because it is higher than all the natures we have mentioned.
In this space, the varying light of the shining stars is thought to be due to some of the stars traveling farther, while others travel nearer in this vast space.
However, those who disagree with this idea say that the space above the air and fire is so subtle, empty, and penetrable that waters cannot exist there, unless, as some mentioned earlier, they are much finer and subtler in form.
To which others respond: What kind of water vapor could ever be lighter than the firmament, no matter how thin it is?
Therefore, others think the firmament is made of solid, firm air, and it is called the firmament because it encloses within itself all the spaces, both solid and empty, light and heavy, that we have mentioned, and supports the waters placed above it, whatever their nature.
However, since there is such varied opinion among scholars on this significant matter, we do not consider any one view to be preferred over another.
Instead, we refer the reader to consider the arguments of both sides.
Chapter FiveAbout the Sun and the Moon
The Mosaic law, or rather, the divine Scripture in the beginning of Genesis, declares that after the appearance of the sea and the land, two great lights were formed in the sky.
It is appropriate, then, that the discussion of the sun and moon follows the firmament in the order of creation, even though in the sequence of creation, they come after the earth and sea.
This aligns with the words of Scripture, although the Catholic faith believes all elements were created timelessly by divine reason.
The sun and the moon are the two lights set in the sky.
The greater light rules the day, while the lesser light governs the night.
However, they do not shine with the same brilliance they had when they were first created.
Throughout their existence, they conserve their light through the cycles of days and nights.
These luminaries, designated by God the Creator for human use, shone with full brilliance when humans lived blamelessly under the Creator's law.
But when humans lost the happiness of paradise due to transgression, these lights also, though not by their own fault, experienced a loss of their brilliance, as Apostle Paul testifies: “For the whole creation groans and suffers together until now” (Romans 8:22).
However, with the coming of the Redeemer, the restoration of original happiness is promised to humanity in an even better way, and it is believed that creation will also regain its ancient beauty.
Thus, the prophet Isaiah, inspired by spiritual insight, says: “And it shall come to pass in that day, when the tower falls, the light of the moon will be like the light of the sun, and the light of the sun will be seven times brighter, like the light of seven days, when the Lord binds up the fracture of His people and heals the wound He inflicted” (Isaiah 30:26).
When the new heaven and new earth are made, Revelation 21:1, and the former things that serve corruption are not remembered, Isaiah 65:17, and the Lord heals the wound of sin and the injury of death in the bodies of those who have been resurrected, Isaiah 30:26, and the proud spirits are cast down from the power they had seized, then the light of the moon will be changed into the light of the sun, and the light of the sun will be restored to the light it had during the seven days of creation.
That is, its light will be restored sevenfold.
For nothing is restored unless it was lost or corrupted; therefore, what the sun and moon lost, they will receive back.
From this, it appears that the luminaries now retain one-seventh of their light, which they will take back sevenfold when, through Habakkuk, the Holy Spirit, placing the past for the future, says: "The sun will rise in its place, and the moon will stand in its order."
For, with the cessation of the changeability of the human condition, which they serve, the changeability of their course will also cease.
For when it is said, "The sun in its place," it indicates that it will never decline at its setting; and when it is said, "The moon will stand in its order," it suggests that it will not suffer the changes of waxing and waning, but will always stand in its order.
This will happen when, as the Apostle says, creation itself will be set free from its bondage to corruption and gain the glorious freedom of the children of God, Romans 8:21.
For when the saints, as a reward for their labor in serving God, are transformed and shine like the sun of righteousness, whose health is everlasting, then even this physical sun will be restored to sevenfold brightness as a reward for its service, to which it was subjected to the bondage of corruption.
Meanwhile, however, in the daily movements of its service, whenever the moon follows the sun, it increases its light; but whenever it precedes the sun, it diminishes its brightness.
The moon has been viewed in various ways: as a half-sphere with one part dark and shadowy, and the other part bright and shining.
The waxing and waning occur such that when the bright part gradually appears, the dark part is hidden, and as the bright part turns, the dark part becomes visible again.
Another perspective is that the moon is round, illuminated by the sun's rays.
When it is near the sun, it shines with the sun's light.
As it moves farther away, its light increases, and when it is fully opposite the sun, it can fully reflect the sun's image.
However, this is not the time or place to discuss the detailed courses of the sun and moon, as this brief work is intended for calculating feast days for almost all readers.
Some believe these celestial bodies are sentient, but common teachings from Catholic authors suggest otherwise.
We must consider which view is more supported by the Holy Scriptures and what most Catholics have accepted in faith.
Opinions that have been equally asserted by Catholics and not contradicted by sacred canon should be left to the readers' judgment.
Chapter SixOn the Upper Space and the Paradise of Heaven
After discussing the firmament and the lights, there is a vast, empty space that stretches from the firmament of heaven down to the earth.
Some writers say this space is divided into two parts: the upper space belongs to heaven, while the lower space is connected to the earth.
The high space that belongs to heaven is very pure and subtle.
It has no clouds, no gusts of wind, no rain, no snow or hail, no changes in the air, no storms, or thunder.
It doesn't even have the air to support flying birds, clouds, or sustain various living beings with breath.
There are no disturbances in the different hemispheres at all.
This is confirmed by those who climb Mount Olympus, the highest peak, unknown to most humans.
They report placing sponges soaked in vinegar around their mouths and noses to help them breathe.
They ascend annually, driven by some unknown superstition.
They say they see no birds, clouds, rain, or wind there.
After completing their rituals, they leave marks in the sands and then return.
When they climb again the next year, they find these marks undisturbed.
This clearly shows there is no disturbed air there, and nothing related to the greenness of plants or shrubs can be found.
However, the place we mentioned earlier, that purest and most refined upper space, should not be considered as the actual existence where no earth can reach or approach.
Instead, this place pertains to the outermost boundaries of this lower space and the nearby confines of that upper space.
In this place, life for those clothed in flesh can by no means dwell.
It is therefore clear that the uppermost, purest, and most tranquil space we discussed earlier, is not meant for those with flesh, nor for mortal things.
Many Catholic authors assert that this space was originally designated for the fallen angels and their leader, because they believe no heavenly angel has fallen from above.
The celestial angels, while in angelic bliss, did not stay there for a time.
As Scripture says, the devil himself was a liar from the beginning (John 8:44) and did not stand in the truth (First John 3:8).
They believe he obtained this place of habitation by lot, with Scripture describing it as a heavenly paradise, speaking under the persona of Prince Cyrus to that highest fallen angel:
"You were perfect in beauty, in the delights of the paradise of God" (Ezekiel 28:13).
Just as men, after their sin, were cast out from the happiness of the earthly paradise and thrust into the cursed habitation of this earth, so that while they sinned on earth, they would later live in the abode of an inferior earth under the punishment of their offense,
so too, the angels, who are thought to have sinned in the purer space of the air, were miserably and unhappily thrown into a lower place, darker and more turbulent than the very air itself.
They are believed to live under the expectation of a future judgment, where they will be more harshly condemned; just as they have airy bodies and now dwell in the air, it is reasonable to think that they once had their seat of beatitude in the air, but in a purer and more refined part.
However, this place, while it belongs to the firmament of the sky, as I mentioned before, is considered part of the sky, just as the Lord Himself testifies, saying: "I saw Satan fall like lightning from heaven" Luke 10:18.
Because of the clear and pure blessedness of that place, Satan was cast out due to his sin and destined for an unhappy and miserable abode in the lower space, that is, the cloudy and stormy air; as the apostle Paul attests, saying: "For our struggle is not against flesh and blood, but against the rulers, against the authorities of this dark world" Ephesians 6:12.
Paul also declares that Christ triumphed over these spiritual forces of evil in the heavenly realms in Himself.
Therefore, the evil spirits, along with their leader the devil, having been cast out from that clear dwelling place among the subcelestial spaces that we mentioned, and after the human race was redeemed from the sin of Adam and each individual's own sin through the coming of the Mediator, some think that this same place is now a place of rest for the souls of the saints while they await the future resurrection.
They even think it is called the heavenly paradise, about which the Lord said to the thief who confessed on the cross: "Truly I tell you, today you will be with me in paradise" Luke 23:43.
Moreover, in that paradise, planted with trees and endowed with a shining fountain, souls freed from their bodies do not need any material sustenance; indeed, the spiritual person, liberated from the carnal use of the mortal body, does not possess it, nor does he need to be refreshed by the fruit-bearing trees of the earthly paradise.
For the eternal does not use the temporal, but contemplates eternal and spiritual things.
We have touched upon these matters not to confirm them but to reflect upon them, especially since we do not attribute to ourselves the clarity of judgment regarding such things.
When the need arises, we can present all 596 authors of these opinions, to whom either belief or doubt can be attributed.
By addressing their views rather than defending them, we strive to reach the truth.
If a better assertion is present, supported more by examples from Scripture or evaluations from knowledgeable Catholics, we are ready to accept it.
But with the previous matters somewhat explained, let's hasten to the following topics.
Chapter SevenAbout the Lower Space and Different Hemispheres.
The lower space is known as the air, which, as we mentioned, is associated with the earth.
It helps sustain the life of all creatures that move through the air on earth, and we can confirm this both within ourselves and through observation.
Sometimes, in the Scriptures, it is also referred to as the earth; as the Psalmist says, when all creatures are urged to praise the Lord, the Creator.
After discussing the higher order of the heavens, the focus shifts to this space of the air.
It is written: "Praise the Lord from the earth, you dragons, and all depths; fire, hail, snow, ice, stormy winds that do his word" Psalm 148:7.
Up to this point, the discussion has been about the air, which is sometimes called the earth.
Afterwards, the Scriptures speak about the soil and the nature of the lower earth with these words: "Mountains and all hills; fruitful trees and all cedars" Psalm 148:9.
The air is often referred to as the earth because of its density and apparent solidity, which supports the bodies of flying birds, even the largest ones, just as fish swim through the waters of the sea.
Thus, birds traverse the spaces of the air by flying.
Everything that water provides to sustain the life of aquatic creatures, the air does for flying creatures.
Just as the reciprocal breath of birds and all that live in the air and on land nourishes and sustains life, so the vital movement of those living in the waters is refreshed through the act of breathing in and out.
Therefore, when creatures are brought into the air, if they do not have the proper breath for air, they quickly perish.
Similarly, those that live in the air cannot survive when air is excluded from them.
As I mentioned, just as the solid nature of the air supports the bodies of flying creatures, it also supports the dense mass of clouds, which often earns it the name "earth." These clouds are sustained by the solid nature of the air, and through this density of air, snow, hail, and ice are produced by the power of cold when it occurs.
When they are drawn into the air, because they do not have a watery breath, they quickly perish; just as those that live in the air cannot survive if the air is taken away from them.
Just as the solid nature of the air supports flying creatures, it also supports the dense mass within itself, which often gives it the name "earth." The dense mass of clouds is sustained, and through this density of air, snow, hail, and ice are produced by the power of cold when it happens.
This space of air has the ability to draw and collect water vapors from the earth and the sea with a smoky lightness, lifting them up high.
As long as they remain in tiny drops, they form clouds, and the air itself suspends them.
But when the wind causes these tiny drops to merge into larger drops, the nature of the air can no longer support them, and they fall to the ground as rain.
If the wind gathers these drops into larger masses before they fall, and they are caught by cold in the clouds, the cold's violence turns them into frozen hailstones.
If the cold reaches the not yet condensed vapors and turns them into drops, it transforms them into snow.
The snow that is nourished in the high clouds, when the air can't support it any longer, and the wind disperses it, falls to the ground.
The Psalmist mentions this, speaking of the Lord:
"He gives snow like wool; He scatters the frost like ashes.
He sends out His ice like crumbs; who can stand before His cold?" (Psalm 147:16-17).
To illustrate that snow, whether on the earth or in the clouds, eventually melts back into water, he later adds:
He sends out His word, and melts them; He causes His wind to blow, and the waters flow (Psalms 147:18).
It's clear that the waters are suspended in the clouds, as written in the book of Job:
He binds up the waters in His clouds, and the cloud does not burst under them (Job 26:8).
However, the air eventually sends those waters back down to the earth and sea, lifting them up from below.
Even though rain draws water from the salty sea, it becomes sweetened through the air.
Just like when salty sea water is poured over the soil (as sailors often do), it immediately changes to fresh water.
Through changes in the air and winds, and by stronger agitation, even fires and thunders are created by hidden commands through angels, who govern the visible world, under the Creator's guidance.
Some believe that thunder occurs because, when there are spaces around the air filled with fire and water—one above and one below—and the air draws both into itself, these opposing elements clash.
Thunder cannot happen without humid clouds and lightning, as clearly seen by observers.
In this clash, fire and water mix, causing terrible sounds and roars; if fire wins, it harms the earth's fruits and trees significantly.
But if water prevails, it retains its fruitful power in trees and crops.
Thunder sounds especially when the fruits of trees and the earth are still in their early stages, before they begin to mature.
The increase or decrease of some creatures, by the command of the Lord Creator, is governed through other creatures.
Chapter EightAbout the Devil and the Nature of Demons.
In this turbulent and foggy region of the air, as we mentioned, the angels who were cast down from their heavenly happiness dwell with their leader.
That leader is called Satan and the devil, while the remaining spirits, who were once angels, are now called demons.
Just as their merits have changed, so have their names and their places; however, even now in the Scriptures, they are often called angels by their old name, because they are messengers of wickedness, just as good spirits are messengers of righteousness.
As it is written in the Gospel: "which my Father prepared for the devil and his angels" (Matthew 25:41).
The Apostle also says: "A thorn in my flesh was given to me, a messenger of Satan, to torment me" (Second Corinthians 12:7).
But these beings, even now, under the expectation of the terrifying arrival of the Lord's judgment, occupy these seats with fear and trembling, although fruitlessly for now, as the apostolic words testify, saying: "Even the demons believe, and they tremble" (James 2:19).
To make it clear that under the expectation of the time in which they will be judged more harshly or rather destroyed, these unclean spirits inhabit this region of the air, who cried out in the presence of the Savior: "What do you want with us, Jesus, Son of God? Have you come here to destroy us before the appointed time?" (Luke 4:34).
At the coming of the eternal judge (when the common prayer of all the saints, saying: "Your will be done on earth as it is in heaven," will be fulfilled), the useless servants will be cast out into outer darkness, as the Lord will expel His adversaries from heaven just as He expelled them from the earth, to whom the punishment of eternal fire has been irremediably prepared by the Father (as the Lord Himself testifies) (Matthew 25:41).
Therefore, they do not deserve forgiveness or redemption because they fell from the highest state of their order.
Once they abandoned their sin, there was nothing left for them to be called back to.
They polluted their happiness, in which they were established, by transgressing the natural good that they were and the Lord's law in which they were created.
Because of this, they neither desire to repent nor could they receive forgiveness even if they did repent.
The human race deserved redemption from its Creator because it fell from a lower rank in its order.
When humanity was placed in the earthly paradise, destined for procreation and the consumption of food, it would have received a better, more sublime, and spiritual life without death, if it had remained obedient to the commandment during that time.
Therefore, the mercy of the Creator calls man back to the state he had not yet reached when he sinned, through the passion of the Lord.
If man had fallen from that higher state, like the angel, he would never be called back again.
The restoration will not be to the rank or order from which the first man fell, but to a more sublime state he hoped for, as the Lord says: "They will be like angels in heaven" This means they will not be like humans in paradise; for into that mortality, assigned to the procreation of offspring and the consumption of food for a time, humans will not return. But after death, rising with spiritual bodies, they will not grow, age, or die, sharing the happiness of the angels.
If we inquire about the time of the devil's transgression, we find that the devil's sin occurred before the time of visible things. Scripture teaches that all things were made simultaneously and without time, as it says: "He who lives forever created all things at once"
In all these things, even that infernal eternal fire, about which the Lord says: "Go into the eternal fire, which my Father has prepared for the devil and his angels" Matthew 25:41, is believed to have been created simultaneously. For when He says, "He created all things at once," He left nothing uncreated among all creatures.
Therefore, the prison that was prepared at the time of creation was made for the one whose sin preceded the very creatures; for the Lord would not have prepared punishment for an innocent being if the sin of that being had not occurred before the punishment was prepared. But He also did this outside of time, He who made the punishment of damnation, by which the runaway servant would be tormented.
This angel, however, when he departed from the Creator's blessedness, lost all the goodness of his nature that he had in his original state; but though he is evil to himself, he always remains good to God, as he obediently, though not willingly, follows the Lord's command because of God's power. From all the goodness of his nature that he had, he now only retains this: that he obeys the Creator God's commands in all things.
But this obedience is not good in the devil and his ministers, who obey only because they cannot disobey; yet this obedience is good in God, whose good will the devil's evil will, when commanded to do good works, cannot resist. But it often happens that when something is commanded by God's good will, the devil's evil will is satisfied in the very same work.
Just as to deceive Ahab, the most wicked king, who was an idolater and persecutor of prophets, when asked how he would deceive, he not only willingly offered himself for this task but also revealed his plan and said:
"I will go and be a lying spirit in the mouths of all his prophets."
And the Lord said: "Go and do so, and you will deceive Ahab"
(Second Chronicles 18:21).
For it was fitting that he, who had put the true prophets of the Lord to death, should perish, deceived by the false words of false prophets.
Behold, the devil promptly offered himself for this wicked task of deceiving the impious, but if he had not been permitted by the Lord, he would not have been able to do this.
The good will of God exercised just vengeance on the holy prophets, while the evil minister fed his own wicked will in the destruction of the wicked and sinful.
But neither among men nor in things subject to men can anything be done without God's permission, as the truth of the Gospel shows, where it is said: "If you cast us out, send us into the herd of pigs"
(Matthew 8:31).
For just as in those men from whom he was expelled, he could not remain against the Lord's command, so also he showed that he could not enter the pigs without His permission.
This is similarly shown in the case of blessed Job and the things he possessed and lost.
In these, the wickedness of the enemy is proven to have done nothing without the Creator’s permission, as it is said: "Have you not made a hedge around him and his house and all his possessions?"
And when the Lord allowed his possessions to be given to the power of the evil enemy, it is added: "Behold, all that he has is in your hand; but do not lay a hand on him"
And Job, understanding these things, responded when he learned of the loss of his possessions:
"The Lord gave, and the Lord has taken away. As the Lord willed, so has He done; blessed be the name of the Lord"
He did not say: The Lord gave, the devil took away; for he knew very well that without God's permission, the adversary could do nothing at all in matters or with people.
But often, in the same task, the wicked will of his adversary feeds itself, and the Lord's goodwill, or just punishment, or fruitful testing is administered.
Under this dual distribution of good and evil will, they punish the wicked and test the good through trials.
For this reason, as long as they still freely fly in this air, up until the time of the final judgment, their punishment is delayed by the Lord.
This is so the wicked among humans may appear as their companions in both crime and punishment, and the good, tested through the tribulations inflicted by them, may be revealed.
Indeed, the wicked and impure spirits, wandering and subtle, are emotionally susceptible and clothed in airy bodies.
Never aging and engaging in hostilities with humans, they swell with pride.
Deceptive and cunning in fraud, they stir human senses, bringing terror to mortals, disturbing life with nightmares, diseases, and distortion of limbs.
They create illusions and oracles, control fate, infuse illicit love and desires into human hearts, and lie with plausible appearances, transforming themselves into the form and light of good angels.
And just as in wickedness, so too do they differ in ranks of power.
Just as good spirits, that is, perfect angels, penetrate the air without suffering, so too would they, if they had not sinned, possess the places they now hold with suffering, subject to themselves, if they lived happily and blessedly.
Even when they speak their names, they take names from the offices and powers of wickedness for themselves.
Just as when the adversary was asked by the Lord for his name in the region of the Gerasenes, he replied, saying: My name is Legion, for we are many
Therefore, it's clear that he didn't state his own name, which he didn't have, but instead used a title that reflected his rank and power.
When the Lord asked, he indicated what was true about him because he couldn't speak otherwise.
Chapter Nine Chapter Nine: On the Nature of Waters and the Flow of the Ocean.
After exploring the expanse of the air and its inhabitants, we now turn our attention to the element of water, which lies between the air and the land.
The gathering of waters, as the Scripture in Genesis declares, is called the sea, for it is written: "And the gatherings of the waters He called seas" (Genesis 1:10).
The part of the waters that flows through springs, rivers, and lakes across the land is fresh, providing drinking water for thirsty animals, supporting various uses, and fertilizing the land to nourish crops.
This is why the rains, which filter through the clouds and fall through the air, become flavorful to better support the growth of crops and quench thirst, as we mentioned earlier.
The part of the waters that remains unchanged and spreads over vast areas of land, where the boundaries of the water are hidden, naturally retains a salty and sharper taste.
This enables it to more effectively nourish fruits and other produce that cannot thrive in fresh water.
Whether the natural taste of water is more flavorful or salty, or equally both, only God knows for certain.
Many believe that the salty taste is the natural flavor of water, while the sweeter taste is thought to be influenced by the nature of the land or air.
However, just as salty water becomes fresh when it flows over the ground, fresh water can become salty when infused with the ashes of marine plants.
Therefore, it is not difficult to believe that both tastes are natural in their own way, since each can transform into the other.
The seas often separate stretches of land, setting boundaries for nations, enriching all provinces with their generous waves, and providing essential trade and exchange among different regions and people.
How closely the ocean's tides align with the movement of the moon is evident to those who observe carefully.
The ocean appears to advance and retreat twice a day within a 24-hour period, divided into cycles of high tide and low tide.
The high tide typically lasts for six hours, consistently rising, and then recedes over the same number of hours.
Conversely, the low tide rises for five hours and recedes over seven hours, leaving the shores it filled empty again.
This pattern aligns so closely with the moon that it always seems to start a new cycle when the moon is in the middle of its phase, which lasts for seven days, twelve hours, and a quarter of a day.
Thus, as the full moon wanes, the low tide also diminishes, splitting into six hundred four dark halves.
However, the high tide is observed in between these phases, never coinciding exactly with the full or new moon.
This results in twenty-four high and low tides each common year.
In a leap year, there are twenty-six of each, as the ocean's movements are inseparably linked with the moon's journey.
Out of these, four tides—two equinoctial high tides and two others at the end of periods of increasing or decreasing daylight—are notably stronger, visibly flooding higher and uncovering more shore than usual.
Since it is impossible for the ocean not to leave some unknown areas, when it floods our lands, it uncovers the same areas as it recedes.
This means that what is considered high tide here is low tide somewhere else, and vice versa, compelling us to admit that we only understand half of the ocean's workings.
But in this and many similar matters, we can only acknowledge the power and vastness of the Creator, who arranged everything by number, weight, and measure Wisdom 11:21.
Meanwhile, with the distinguished teacher of the Gentiles, we say: "For we know in part and we prophesy in part. But when what is perfect comes, then I will know fully, just as I am fully known" First Corinthians 13:9.
Moreover, the scripture of Genesis declares that various kinds of fish and birds, meaning all aquatic and flying creatures, were made from this watery element. But philosophers who study the nature of things count 153 kinds of fish, that is, all creatures that live in water, which the apostolic net had gathered as if from every kind of fish.
As for the birds, whether they have this number of species, or a larger or smaller number, although some may estimate, they cannot confirm it with great authority; thus, they are neither to be followed nor rejected. However, since the origin of all birds came from water, how did such diverse habits of living, dwelling, or swimming arise? Some always float on salty waves and find their sustenance there; others live in the still waters of lakes and rivers. Others live on land without any habit of swimming, some in fields, some in forests, some in mountains, and some in marshy places. Some cannot lift themselves with their wings to fly, while others reach the highest and most remote parts of the air by flying, so that in summer they even bring snow from the highest clouds with their wings.
Despite their vastly different origins, all birds, regardless of their connection to water, thrive in varied conditions.
Some come from salty water, some from fresh water, some from the dew of plants, some from the condensation of trees, some from the moisture of marshes, some from the confluence of mountains, some from the vapor of the air, and some from the fluid conspiracy of the highest clouds.
Each bird naturally adapts to the environment that matches its origin, living in and deriving sustenance from the place it was first created.
Chapter TenAbout Paradise
Since the earth was organized after the waters, let's first talk about Paradise, where the first humans lived.
Although this topic could be brief, there are many opinions on whether the immortal life granted to humans before sin was called Paradise, or if the entire world was so perfectly arranged for innocent living that it was named Paradise.
As long as the inhabitants lived blamelessly, their earthly home provided everything happily without any labor.
But after they sinned and changed for the worse, the world was also altered and obscured by their fault and the judgment of punishment, much like we discussed about the sun and moon.
It lost much of its beauty and fruitful power.
What once supported the happiness and well-being of the righteous now brought punishment to the wicked.
Or was there a spiritual place, full of blessed happiness, prepared for humans who maintained the merit of their creation, where nothing harmed their bodily happiness as long as they followed the commandment?
The authority of the Scriptures of Genesis supports this view, saying: "The Lord God had planted a garden in Eden, in the east, where he placed the man he had formed" (Genesis 2:8).
From the beginning, Paradise is said to have been planted, suggesting this place holds a special primacy in the world, where the first man is believed to have been placed immediately after his creation.
Indeed, it was fitting that the head and beginning of the human race be placed in the head and beginning of the world, so that the growth of humanity would start from there, just as the world they inhabit began.
The state of paradise, as described in Scripture, is depicted as being filled with fruit-bearing trees and adorned with a great fountain that waters the whole face of the earth.
It narrates about the man placed there:
"Eat from any tree in the garden" (Genesis 2:16).
The woman said, "We eat from the fruit of the trees in the garden" (Genesis 3:2).
And earlier it states: "And a fountain rose from the earth, watering the entire surface of the ground" (Genesis 2:6).
In these passages, with a straightforward historical account, what would prevent the truth of Scripture from being preserved, just as it shines through in all its accounts about the beginning of the entire visible creation?
We believe, as Genesis investigates historically, in the creation of the firmament, the sea, the earth, the lights, the stars, the aquatic creatures, the land animals, and man himself.
Why should we not accept the mention of paradise filled with fruit-bearing trees and adorned with a great fountain, unless it's considered a riddle?
This can be understood in both ways: according to the historical narration of events and according to tropology, which is a moral explanation.
Sacred Scripture can be understood in three ways:
The first is purely according to the letter, without any figurative intention, as Saint Jerome says: "The Acts of the Apostles indeed seem to me to sound like a bare history."
The second way is through a figurative understanding, without regard to the actual events, such as the beginning and end of Ezekiel, the Song of Songs, and some parables of the Gospel, which speak one thing and mean another.
The third way preserves the historical narration of events while understanding it in a mystical sense, just as the ark of Noah, the tabernacle, and the temple were made historically, and intellectually the mysteries of the Church are designated through these.
Thus, the location of the paradise of the first Adam, which existed as a symbol of the future, and of the future Church, which is the land of the second Adam, prefigured mysteries.
While man lived there immortally and happily, wouldn’t the subjugation of the entire world also be subject to him?
For what would prevent him from entering the world, who would not fear being harmed by creatures?
Fire would not burn him, water would not drown him, the strength of beasts would not kill him, thorns or stings would not wound him, the absence of air would not suffocate him, and nothing that harms mortals would hinder him.
An immortal and invulnerable body would face no threats of death, wounds, or injury from any creatures, as long as he did not offend the Creator through disobedience.
Therefore, what would stop the inhabitant of paradise from examining all things that were subject to him, when the Lord not only did not forbid it but commanded it, saying: "Be fruitful, and multiply, and fill the earth, and subdue it; and have dominion over the fish of the sea, and over the birds of the air" (Genesis 1:28)?
Just as it is free for angels to move about in the realms subject to them from their seat in heaven, and yet they have their seats in heaven, why would it be difficult for humans placed in paradise to move about all creation subject to them without any effort?
Just as they possessed bodies immune to pain, aging, and death, they also had bodies free from all toil and laziness.
But truly, when the inhabitant of paradise committed sin in his place of earthly happiness, he was banished to the cursed earth and immediately lost some of the things he had possessed before, while he preserved others with effort.
Having been excluded from the seat of blessedness, the possibility of returning was blocked.
Thus, just as the apostate angel, cast down with his followers from the highest serenity of his paradise, was allotted the gloomy place of this air, so too was man cast down from the earthly happiness of his paradise to the cursed earth.
When the inhabitant of paradise sinned in his place of earthly happiness, he was cast down to the accursed earth.
Immediately, he lost some of the things he previously possessed, while others he had to labor to keep.
Being excluded from the seat of blessedness, the possibility of returning was blocked.
Just as the apostate angel and his followers were cast down from the serenity of paradise to the gloomy place of this air, man too was cast down from his earthly paradise to the accursed earth.
As it is written:
"And the Lord God drove him out of paradise and placed him on the earth from which he was taken. He set cherubim before paradise, with a flaming sword that turned every way, to guard the way to the tree of life" (Genesis 3:23).
This shows that although cherubim are said to guard the way to the tree of life, they are also commanded to defend the entire paradise, as Scripture indicates the flaming sword is placed not only before the tree of life but before the whole of paradise.
It is not entirely clear from which specific tree Adam ate, but it is clear that immediately after the sin, he covered his nakedness with fig leaves.
This tree alone, in the time of his flesh, the Lord Jesus cursed shortly before his death for Adam's sin, and it quickly withered when he said: "May no fruit ever come from you again" (Matthew 21:19).
This means it could no longer harm humans, just as the devil.
Behold, Christ gathered the curse of Adam's sin upon this tree, the fig tree, which infected the whole earth before he purified it with the dew of his blood.
However, whether man first received the blame from this tree or another, God alone knows for certain.
Whatever the tree of the knowledge of good and evil might be now, it shouldn't be thought that it can harm people today as much as it could harm those in paradise then.
Eating from this tree can lead to death, but it's not because the tree itself is deadly or because it gives the knowledge of good and evil.
It's the disobedience to the Lord's command not to eat from the tree that brings death.
Obedience to God's command meant knowing good, while disobedience led to knowing evil.
However, humanity couldn't understand the difference without transgressing; when people only knew good, they didn't understand what evil was or how it could harm them.
To show that there was nothing harmful in the tree itself, note that it's not the tree but the way to the tree of life that's barred.
This exclusion represents the merciful forgiveness of the original sin.
If humanity had eaten from the tree of life after committing the original sin, they would've been stuck in a miserable, eternal state, unable to remove the stain of sin.
The Lord provided no other way to erase this sin except through death, which He planned to overcome through the coming of His Son, Jesus Christ.
Through Jesus's death, our guilt would die, and through His resurrection, the law of death would be annulled.
By His ascension, immortality would be granted to humanity, and we would receive the angelic and spiritual life prepared for us from the beginning.
This is affirmed when the Lord says to those on His right in the final judgment: "Come, blessed of my Father, inherit the kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the world."
Chapter ElevenAbout the location of the world inhabited by humanity
Regarding the location of the world inhabited by humanity, the Psalmist says to the Lord:
"You established the earth on its foundations; it will never be moved. The deep covered it like a garment; the waters stood above the mountains" Psalm 104:5-6.
This indicates that the earth is founded not on the stability of another element but on its own stability and firmness.
Whether anything is placed beneath it, such as the waters, and the waters beneath the air, and the air beneath the upper space, and that beneath the firmament, and the firmament beneath the upper waters, only He knows, who sees all things everywhere and from every angle.
Many authors have reported that the part of the world given to humans to inhabit is divided into four parts.
The names of these four parts, as wise men understand, begin with the four letters of the name of the first man, namely, Adam.
That is, Anatole, Dysis, Arctus, and Mesimbria, which mean East, North, South, and West.
It was fitting that the one who filled the whole earth with his kind would have in his name the names of the four parts of the world.
The four seasons of the year are also distinguished in an annual sequence, and with the completion of the year, the management of the earthly world always returns in a cycle without cessation.
In spring, the time when the world was created, it always blooms;
in summer, it blossoms and bears fruit;
in autumn, it ripens and provides its fruits for human use;
in winter, it withers and dries up.
However, it endures this cycle of growth and decline as long as it is subjected to the bondage of corruption and is bound to the service of mortals.
When humans are no longer born or die, the earth will stop experiencing cycles of growth and decline.
At that time, the prophecy of Isaiah, or rather the Lord's prophecy through Isaiah, will come true:
"Behold, I create new heavens and a new earth, and the former things will not be remembered, but you will rejoice and be glad in what I create."
Isaiah 65:17-18.
Humans, living spiritually with transformed bodies, will need to live in better, spiritual places.
As Paul says, this body is sown in corruption but will be raised in incorruption. It is sown a natural body, but it will be raised a spiritual body; it is sown in dishonor, but it will be raised in glory. For this corruptible must put on incorruption, and this mortal must put on immortality.
First Corinthians 15:42 and following.
When corruption and mortality no longer exist in our bodies, we will not need mortal and corruptible things. This is confirmed by the holy Gospels, as shown in the resurrection of the Lord's body, when the linens He was wrapped in were found alone in the tomb after His resurrection.
As it is said of Peter: "And he saw the linens alone, and went away, marveling at what had happened."
John 20:5.
Therefore, with new bodies that don't need what a corruptible life requires, a new earth with a new heaven will be created to live in. The nature and surface of this earth will be restored to a spiritual state, fitting for spiritual beings, without any changeability.
But when will this happen?
When Jerusalem is praised on earth, its people rejoice and are glad, and when the saints celebrate what the Lord has created, their sun will not set, and the moon will not wane.
When those redeemed by the Lord come to Zion with praise, eternal joy will be upon their heads, and they will obtain joy and gladness, while sorrow and sighing will flee away.
The days of their mourning are completed, and those who mourn are comforted.
God will wipe away every tear from the faces of the saints, and He will remove the disgrace of His people.
The sorrow of those mourning in Zion will be taken away, and they will receive a crown instead of ashes, the oil of joy instead of mourning, a garment of praise instead of a spirit of despair, and they will be called strong in righteousness.
When the blessed come to the right hand, they will shine like the sun in the kingdom of their Father.
Chapter TweleveOn the Nature of Humans After Sin
Humans, destined to live in this world after original sin, did not lose all the natural good they originally had.
Instead, corrupted first by the sin of their ancestor and further ruined by depraved habits, they now find that just as they gain the fruits of the cursed earth with labor, they can only preserve the natural good within them with painstaking effort.
Just as they fell in three ways through the disobedience of the first human, the serpent, the woman, and the consenting man, so too are all their descendants afflicted by three wounds: pain, old age, and death.
They struggle to preserve with great vigilance any good that was naturally implanted in them by the Creator and is found through diligent effort.
Any good they find through God's grace, except for unjust wealth, they do not leave to their heirs.
All the skills they acquire in life are lost equally at the end of this life when the spirit departs.
In the same condition of weakness, both the poor and kings, the foolish and the wise, are afflicted.
For all alike need sleep, food for sustenance, and clothing to wear.
They are either burdened or corrupted by the passions of carnal vices and are troubled by the emotions of the mind, such as anger, love, desire, and fear.
They are weakened by pain, old age, and death.
They quickly shed the past, use the present only a little, and await the uncertain future.
In the same way, they sense and live through hearing, sight, touch, taste, and smell.
They are bound by the same connection of original sin and enriched by the same gift of the Redeemer.
They are cleansed by the waters of baptism and the Holy Spirit.
But for those who neglect the faith of redemption or the works of faith, eternal punishment is due, just like it is for the transgressing angels and the devil, their prince.
However, for those who uphold the rights of the original condition, whether through the teachings of Scripture or the good defenses of nature, a life prepared by the gift of the Redeemer awaits in the future.
Chapter Thirteen On the diversity of sinners and the place of punishments.
Because the nature of sins varies, some crimes can be cleansed through the fire of judgment, while others must be punished by the fire of eternity.
Among these, some are deemed worthy of eternal punishment, some do not reach judgment, and some, after the examination of judgment, face perpetual damnation, as the Apostle Paul says:
"Some people's sins are obvious, preceding them to judgment, but the sins of others follow them" Timothy 5:24.
Regarding those who lack judgment, the Lord Himself testified and said:
"Whoever does not believe in the Son is already judged" John 3:18.
Therefore, it is understood that those who do not merit faith and do not receive the grace of baptism will not face future judgment but will depart from this life judged by the word of the Gospel, which says:
"Truly, truly, I say to you, unless one is born of water and the Spirit, he cannot enter the kingdom of God" John 3:3.
The words of the Psalmist are also consistent with this, where it is said:
"The wicked will not stand in the judgment" Psalm 1:5.
However, those who are burdened by the multitude of sins after the cleansing of baptism are divided into two groups:
some of them are judged by the words of the Holy Scripture before they depart from this life, about whom the Apostle Paul speaks, saying:
"Do not be deceived: neither the sexually immoral, nor idolaters, nor adulterers, nor men who practice homosexuality, nor thieves, nor the greedy, nor drunkards, nor slanderers, nor swindlers will inherit the kingdom of God" First Corinthians 6:9.
Those who commit such and similar deadly sins without remedy until death will be judged from this life into eternal punishments.
Concerning whose guilt, the Lord's close companion John speaks:
"There is a sin that leads to death; I do not say that one should pray for that" First John 5:16.
For sin leads to death, as anyone who neglects to repent for past crimes at the end of their life will find.
And it should be noted, according to the Apostle James, that whoever offends in one of these points has become guilty of all.
For He who said, "You shall not commit adultery," also said, "You shall not kill." So if you do not commit adultery but you do kill, you have become a transgressor of the law James 2:10.
Some, however, who are not involved in these serious crimes, are reserved for the final divine judgment and leave this world, yet they still face the sentence of eternal damnation from the supreme judge. These are the ones who, ignoring works of mercy, do not feed Christ in the poor with food or drink, do not clothe them, do not take them in as guests, and do not bring comfort to those who are sick, bound in chains, or in prison. For this, they will hear from Him: "Depart from me, you cursed, into the eternal fire prepared for the devil and his angels" Matthew 25:41.
For it is not enough to abstain from doing evil to desire the kingdom of heaven; one must also take care to do good. For through the prophet Isaiah, the Lord equally commands: "Cease to do evil, learn to do good" Isaiah 1:16. The Spirit of the Lord also harmonizes these same words through the Psalmist, saying: "Turn away from evil and do good" Psalm 37:27.
To show that after the terror of this dreadful sentence we have foretold, no repentance could sway the judge, it is thus added at the end of the entire discussion: "Then they will go away to eternal punishment" Matthew 25:46.
Regarding that place of eternal fire, the dungeon of hell, many have said it is a physical place where the bodies of sinners will be tortured. For if that fire were not physical and in a place, how could it hold the tortured bodies of those who will be resurrected, in which the truth of corporality will be so susceptible to suffering that it will be subject to the gnashing of teeth and lamentable weeping? As the words of the Lord and judge declare, saying: "Cast the worthless servant into the outer darkness."
There will be weeping and gnashing of teeth Mark 25:30
Where their worm does not die, and the fire is not quenched Isaiah 66:24; Mark 9:45
In this place, it is said to the king of Babylon through the Prophet: "Beneath you, the moth is spread out, and worms are your covering" Isaiah 14:11
Someone also said: "Just as the depths of the sea are to the earth, so the depths of the earth are to the underworld."
Hence, it seems to be written about that which is written: "No one in heaven, nor on earth, nor under the earth was found who could open the book and break its seals" Revelation 5:2
Therefore, it is clearly evident that this place, whatever kind it may be, is under the earth, which is called the lower hell and the land of forgetfulness.
But this fire, since it is said to be prepared for the devil and his angels, what kind of physical nature must it have to torment angels? Also, the soul of the rich man, stripped of the body, is described as being tormented by that infernal fire, when he said: "For I am in agony in this flame" Luke 16:24
Unless perhaps that fire and place have such power that they can torment and hold angels, souls, and bodies in the same way. Or certainly, when it is said about the children of the resurrection and eternal happiness: "They will be like angels in heaven" Mark 12:25
Indeed, the children of eternal damnation, when they have taken back their bodies for the punishment of eternal fire, will themselves be like demons in hell; so that the children of the good resurrection, being children of God, will join the company of good angels, and the children of eternal death, being children of the devil, will join the company of Satan's angels.
About whom it is said: "They will be gathered together as prisoners in a pit, and will be shut up in prison, and after many days they will be visited" Isaiah 2422
Whether this is to increase or decrease their punishments, we do not know.
Chapter FourteenOn Purgatorial Fire
Those who receive the comforts of eternal life will also experience the happiness of the kingdom of heaven in two ways through the gift of generosity.
For some, while still living on earth, when they become poor for Christ, the kingdom of heaven is not just a future promise but is given to them even now, as they persevere in labor and fatigue.
As it is said: "Blessed are the poor in spirit, for theirs is the kingdom of heaven" (Matthew 5:3).
Similarly, those who endure persecution for righteousness also rejoice in the same reward, as it is added: "Blessed are those who are persecuted for righteousness' sake, for theirs is the kingdom of heaven" (Matthew 5:10).
He did not say "theirs will be," implying a future reward, but when they depart from their bodies, they will receive what they already possess now through the gift of the giver.
Therefore, it is said to those still living on earth: "Whatever you bind on earth will be bound in heaven, and whatever you loose on earth will be loosed in heaven" (Matthew 18:18).
It means that the kingdom of heaven is yours while you still live on earth.
Whoever you free from sins can become its possessor, and whoever you exclude, destined for destruction, will be excluded from that same kingdom.
Therefore, the Lord commanded: "Rejoice and be glad, for your names are written in heaven" (Matthew 5:12).
Since your names are removed from earthly companionship for the sake of the heavenly kingdom, it is necessary for you to be written as heirs of the eternal homeland in the meantime.
So, those who endure all the hardships and evils in this life will enter eternal rest without any further trials, or, so to speak, without a summons.
By whose grace, some will be called after purification, and they will possess endless comfort.
After the examination, they will hear: "Come, you who are blessed by my Father; take your inheritance, the kingdom" (Matthew 25:34).
They will be worthy to possess this because of their kindness to the poor, and indeed to Christ in the poor, by giving food to the hungry, drink to the thirsty, clothing to the naked, shelter to the wanderer, and visiting the sick and imprisoned Christ in their least brothers.
In their calling, it is evident that up to now, they have been somewhat distant from Christ, even though they were placed on His right hand.
Later, the supreme judge will say to them: "Come, you who are blessed" (Matthew 25:34).
It is as if He were saying: "You, who until now have been somewhat distant from salvation due to the need for purification by the fire of judgment, now having been thoroughly examined and cleansed from every stain of guilt, come closer and enter."
The Lord Himself does not deny that some sins will be forgiven in the future, as it is said: "But whoever blasphemes against the Holy Spirit will never be forgiven; they are guilty of an eternal sin" (Mark 3:29).
From this, it is understood that there are certain sins that, although not forgiven in this world, can be erased in the future judgment by fire.
Otherwise, the Lord would not have made this distinction.
About this fire, John the Baptist, the forerunner of the Lord's coming, speaks to the Jews: "After me comes one who is more powerful than I, whose sandals I am not worthy to carry. He will baptize you with the Holy Spirit and fire" (Matthew 3:11).
This means: He will wash away or forgive your past sins with the Holy Spirit through the baptism of water, and some of the sins that follow will be purged by the purgatorial fire.
Regarding that fire, which is kindled not to cleanse the wicked who are judged, but to destroy the condemned, John adds a little later:
"His winnowing fork is in his hand, and he will thoroughly clean his threshing floor, and gather his wheat into the barn; but he will burn the chaff with unquenchable fire"
(Matthew 3:12; Luke 3:17).
It is one thing to be baptized with fire, and another to be burned with unquenchable fire.
About this fire, John also says:
"Every tree that does not bear good fruit is cut down and thrown into the fire"
(Matthew 3:10).
But about the fire of purification, the Lord himself speaks in the Gospel:
"But anyone who says, 'You fool!' will be in danger of the fire of hell"
(Matthew 5:22).
He did not say eternal fire because it is believed that this sin is punished by purgatorial fire rather than eternal flame.
About this difference, between those whom the fire of the future will not touch and those who will receive salvation after suffering the loss by fire, the Apostle Paul explains, saying:
"For no one can lay any foundation other than the one already laid, which is Jesus Christ. If anyone builds on this foundation using gold, silver, precious stones, wood, hay, or straw, their work will be shown for what it is, because the Day will bring it to light. It will be revealed with fire, and the fire will test the quality of each person’s work. If what has been built survives, the builder will receive a reward. If it is burned up, the builder will suffer loss but yet will be saved—even though only as one escaping through the flames"
(First Corinthians 3:12 and following).
Through these two types of buildings, that is, gold, silver, and precious stones, as well as wood, hay, and straw, perfect and less perfect works built upon the faith of Christ are indicated; but those works, which are represented by wood, hay, and straw, although fragile, are not shown to be polluted.
From this, it is understood that not the major sins, which stain those whose doers Paul excluded from the kingdom of God, but those which do not harm much, although they build up less, can be indicated by these:
Using lawful marriage more than necessary; eating excessively; being overly happy; getting angry to the point of speaking intemperately; taking too much pleasure in one's possessions; being less diligent in prayer than required; getting up later than appropriate; laughing excessively; indulging in more sleep than necessary; remaining silent about the truth; speaking idle words; thinking something is true when it is not; approving what you thought was false in matters not related to faith; negligently forgetting to do good; having a disordered appearance.
These, and similar things, are sins that can be purged by fire.
It cannot be denied, and their doer, if not burdened by greater sins, is thus thought to be saved as if through fire.
Penitents, at the very end of their present life, whether they receive full remission of sins here, or whether their faults are erased by purgatorial fire, He knows who, seeing the reins and hearts, considers the worthiness of repentance, who responded to the thief on the cross, almost without time, without a penitent work: Today you will be with me in paradise.
And to Ezekiel, He says: On whatever day the wicked turns away from his wickedness, I will not remember any of the iniquities he has committed.
But regarding that purgatorial fire, it must be noted that it is longer and sharper than any torment that man can imagine in the present.
Luke 23:43.
Ezekiel 33:12.
Chapter FifteenOn the Future Life
The Holy Scripture talks about the true happiness of the future life:
"What no eye has seen, nor ear heard, nor the heart of man conceived, what God has prepared for those who love him" (First Corinthians 2:9).
About which the Lord said:
"They will be like the angels in heaven" (Mark 12:25).
The same Lord spoke even more about these things:
"Then the righteous will shine like the sun in the kingdom of their Father" (Matthew 13:43).
Indeed, the sun of righteousness will rise for those who fear the name of the Lord.
In whose wings is healing, who on the mountain made the faces of Moses and Elijah shine before the apostles, to whom the saints, when they suffer with Him, will also be glorified together.
As previously stated:
"They will be like the angels in heaven" (Mark 12:25).
This means that just as the angels, who were initially changeable by nature, as proven by those who fell, are now unchangeable, so they neither fear to sin nor can sin, being made so by the contemplation of God.
Likewise, humans, who were created changeable by nature, as shown in Adam and his descendants, will be made unchangeable by the contemplation of the Creator after the resurrection.
So they will neither desire to sin nor be able to sin; for every rational creature that is refreshed by the contemplation of God cannot sin.
Not that the angels and humans, who are free from fault, lack free will; for in that life, they do whatever they want, but they cannot want anything that is not good.
Hence, because they never will evil, they never commit any sin.
This perfect good will is made perfect through the contemplation of the supreme Creator.
What the creature could not have by itself is granted by the gift of the Giver.
From this, it is clear that the angels or humans who sinned either in heaven or in paradise did not see God.
For if they had seen Him, they could by no means have sinned afterward.
But in response, someone might strongly say:
Why then, after seeing the vision of glory that made Moses' face shine in the wilderness, did he stumble at the waters of Meribah?
And why did Peter, after witnessing the glory of the Only Begotten on the mountain with Moses and Elijah, deny the Lord in the courtyard of the priests?
This question is easily answered by noting that Moses saw the back of the glory through an angel or some other creature.
Peter and the other disciples saw the divinity of Christ shining through his human body; for if they had seen the divinity itself, they would not have been able to live in the flesh afterward.
For the Lord himself answered Moses:
No one can see my face and live Exodus 33:20.
Therefore, the holy ones after the resurrection will not see the Lord through symbols and enigmas, as the distinguished Teacher of the Gentiles declares:
For now we see through a mirror, dimly; but then face to face.
Now I know in part, but then I shall know just as I also am known First Corinthians 13:12.
Just as the powerful companion of the Lord's heart, John, said:
We shall see him as he is First John 3:2;
when what is promised to the Church through the prophet Isaiah will be fulfilled:
The sun shall no longer be your light by day, nor for brightness shall the moon give light to you; but the Lord will be to you an everlasting light, and your God your glory Isaiah 60:19.
From this, we understand that the Church will be illuminated not by creatures, but by the majesty of the Lord Himself.
When it partakes in the serenity of perpetual happiness, it will be secure in the dignity of angelic company.
In this serenity, it will possess all good things without the pressure of any accusation.
Light will not be obscured by darkness, life will not end in death, health will not be marred by pain, joy will not be diminished by sorrow, youth will not be affected by old age, the absence of loved ones will not dim love, beauty will not be degraded by any flaw, strength will not be weakened by infirmity, and justice will not be corrupted by sin.
Beyond these things, there will be aspects that no human thought or reasoning can currently grasp while still on earth.
Among all these creatures, whose order we have briefly mentioned, the Creator made some from nothing and some from pre-existing matter.
He created the heavens, the earth, the sea, and everything made from them, from formless matter.
But the formless matter itself, the orders of angels we previously mentioned, and the human soul, He made from nothing.
For God did not create the soul either from Himself or from any underlying material of physical creatures, because we believe it is not a part of God, but a creation of God.
If God had made it from Himself, it would not be subject to suffering, change, and misery.
Likewise, if He had created it from physical creatures, it would possess something physical in its nature, whether heat from fire, breath from air, moisture from water, or density and solidity from earth.
But since it lacks all these things, it is agreed that it was created incorporeal.
Through this incorporeality, it is recognized to have the same substance as angels, and therefore shares their eternity, mutability, and power of free will.
This image of God does not possess an eternity but retains a similarity in free will, as the Prophet commemorates this image of God impressed upon us, saying: "The light of Your countenance has been signed upon us" Psalms 4:7.
Whether individual souls are sent by God to each body separately, or whether they come from Adam and from parents, just like the bodies of those being born, has been debated by many wise men.
Yet, they have left nothing in this matter to which more faith could be given.
So why should we attempt to resolve such a great and dangerous issue, or what benefit would it bring us to involve ourselves in these convolutions, where each side defeats the other without being able to establish their own explanations?
Therefore, to avoid reaching beyond our capacity, let us leave this question, which many writers have declared unsolvable, to the knowledge of the Creator.
For whatever the eater of the Paschal Lamb's flesh could not consume, the consuming flame on the next day devours.
This signifies that all matters which escape our investigative knowledge of the sacred Scriptures are illuminated and completed by the fire of divine wisdom.
Even those things which we, through a small window of our senses and wisdom, have touched upon by some prior illumination of His grace, we cannot fully know as we should.
For we know in part, as long as we are in this world.
Yet, if we reach that inestimable light of the Father of lights, then we shall know as we are known.
But even the things we have grasped through our limited senses and wisdom, thanks to some prior illumination of His grace, we aren't able to know perfectly as we should; for we only know in part while we are in this world.
However, if we reach the inestimable light of the Father of lights, then we will know as we are known.
Behold, venerable Father, regarding the order of creatures you asked me about, I have responded briefly and concisely according to my limited ability.
I will repay the reward of this small gift with your prayers.
Not because my insignificant service can offer anything truly worthy of your obedience, veneration, and authority, but because it fulfills the efforts of obedience, even if it cannot achieve everything.
For in the treasury of the temple, the small gift of the poor widow is preferred over the abundant gold of many rich people.
And in the gilded tabernacle, where silver, precious gems, fine linen, and purple, blue, and scarlet fabrics are offered, the diligence of those who bring goat skins is also not despised.
Therefore, do not disdain the obedience of my smallness in the calm harbor of your heart, and do not hesitate to steer the small boat of this present work against the unstable waves of those who chatter.
For I, agreeing with good and Catholic readers, do not care about the complaints of the envious, who crawl on the ground without wings, mocking the nests of birds like frogs in flight.
Protected by the shield of your reason, and armed with the support of the Lord, I will take care to hasten safely on both sides to my homeland.
For those who seek to please God, we do not fear the threats of men at all.
Thanks be to God.
Amen.